<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Thomas Chatting</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2022-09-30T21:59:33+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Thomas Chatting</name>
   <email>thomas.chatting@icloud.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>two thousand and twenty two 🏕️</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/29/two-thousand-and-twenty-two/"/>
   <updated>2022-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/29/two-thousand-and-twenty-two</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe allow="autoplay *; encrypted-media *; fullscreen *; clipboard-write" frameborder="0" height="175" style="width:100%;max-width:660px;overflow:hidden;background:transparent;" sandbox="allow-forms allow-popups allow-same-origin allow-scripts allow-storage-access-by-user-activation allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation" src="https://embed.music.apple.com/gb/album/black-dog/1502254966?i=1502254973"></iframe>

<p>Quick note: I’ve noticed that YouTube are clamping down super hard on embedding music, which sucks. The YouTube link to the above song is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QOu0Ht0-D4M">here</a>.</p>

<p>I went kind of hard on neglecting this website, other than quietly changing the style a couple of times when I got an <em>itch</em>.</p>

<p>This year I’ve pivoted career within IT to <em>Business Intelligence</em>, more specifically: Data Warehousing. I think in 🇺🇸 it’s more known as Data Science, though I’d probably be considered more of a “dba”. The pace is very different to working in IT Operations (which was basically retail), and I’m really settled into the role after six months. To quote a manager “you get to chill out and make some cool shit”.</p>

<p>We’ve also taken the little one on a camping trip. This was way too much fun, weirdly even the five hour drive down to North Norfolk (Aha!).</p>

<p class="center-text"><img alt="A map showing Hunstanton in The Wash of the United Kingdom's east coast" src="/static/images/IMG_2243.jpg" /></p>

<p>After getting each other some proper walking boots on our birthdays, we’ve also taken up hiking. Me and the guys climbed the 16km <a href="https://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/marsden-moor-estate/trails/standedge-circuit-walk">Standedge Circuit</a> (435 m), armed with tuna sandwiches, whiskey and plenty of beer on my birthday, then more recently on Jenni’s birthday we climbed Pen-y-ghent (694 m). Both have very short, sharp scrambles and beautiful views.</p>

<h2 id="anyway">anyway</h2>

<p>There’s a lot of articles I’ve been reading for work (and not for work) which led to the inspiration for me to take fingers-to-keyboard and update/write for this blog again. I’ll try to share them Soon™️, however no promises as the little one has nearly finished her Turkey Dinosaurs and Chips so it’s nearly story time.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ubuntu portable setup and hardening 🐧</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/tech/2021/04/06/ubuntu-portable-hardened/"/>
   <updated>2021-04-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/tech/2021/04/06/ubuntu-portable-hardened</id>
    <content type="html"><p>While I’ve recently mentioned how I’ve been doing some work from a mid-2010 Unibody MacBook, I also like to use my more modern HP Envy 13. The problem is, as mentioned before, that it’s become a Sims 4 box that I don’t always have access to. Also, disk space on a machine with such a small HD and a big thicc Windows 10 install can be quite tight.</p>

<p>Anyway, below I chronicle the process of installing an OS onto a USB stick, and then hardening it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Hardening” is the process of better securing your operating system/hardware.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="table-of-contents">table of contents</h2>

<ol>
  <li><a href="#setup">the setup</a></li>
  <li><a href="#install">installing ubuntu</a></li>
  <li><a href="#harden">hardening ubuntu</a>
    <ol>
      <li><a href="#livepatch">enable livepatch</a></li>
      <li><a href="#updates">check for updates</a></li>
      <li><a href="#avahi">remove avahi</a></li>
      <li><a href="#madagascar">make like madagascar</a>
        <ol>
          <li><a href="#ufwdeny">deny all inbound and outbound connections</a></li>
          <li><a href="#ufwinterface">find your interface</a></li>
          <li><a href="#ufwexceptions">create firewall exceptions and force external dns</a></li>
          <li><a href="#ufwlogs">monitor firewall logs</a></li>
        </ol>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#todo">next steps (and todo)</a></li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h2 id="setup"><a id="setup"></a>setup</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/SanDisk-Ultra-Drive-Type-C-devices/dp/B07YYJRXQR/ref=sr_1_4?crid=A0ZKIWP768CI&amp;dchild=1&amp;keywords=sandisk+ultra+dual+drive+usb+type-c&amp;qid=1615329676&amp;sprefix=sandisk+ultra+dual+%2Caps%2C162&amp;sr=8-4">Here is an Amazon UK link to the USB stick I went with.</a></p>

<p>This stick seemed to have the most recommendations when I searched for “Best USB stick to run an OS from”.</p>

<p><img src="/static/images/ubuntu-hardening-desktop.png" alt="a screenshot from ubuntu desktop 20.04 LTS" /></p>

<p>I went with Ubuntu 20.04 LTS because of its great hardware support, easy hardening options, and also due to the fact I’ve used Ubuntu/Xubuntu on-and-off for 15 years.</p>

<h2 id="installing-ubuntu"><a id="install"></a>installing ubuntu</h2>

<p>I lost my (now secondary) USB stick. It’s somewhere in the house but I think there’s a distinct possibility it’s inside my daughters intestinal tract. Or she’s just hidden it from me. Anyway, I used VirtualBox to install Ubuntu onto the USB stick.</p>

<p>Use Disk Manager in Windows 10 or gparted or your disk manager of choice to remove all partitions and data from the USB stick.</p>

<p>Uninstall WireShark if you have it. Install VirtualBox and the Additions extension pack to enable USB 3 support. <strong>Restart the host machine</strong>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This bit took me absolutely ages and I nearly resorted to buying an extra USB stick. Persevere with the steps above and use any errors VBox gives you to find people with the same issue.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Create a virtual machine with at least 2 GB RAM with no hard disk. Enable networking. Enable USB 3 support and create a filter for your USB stick. Unplug the USB stick and boot the machine from the Ubuntu 20.04 live USB ISO. Once loaded, plug the USB stick back in.</p>

<p>From here, you should be able to install Ubuntu using the defaults. I selected Minimal Installation, unchecked the proprietary software option, and selected the option to encrypt my disk.</p>

<p>As I had chosen to encrypt the disk, I created a user account with a different strong passphrase and allowed auto login. I have enabled live patch which meant I have setup another strong passphrase, and the account password uses another strong passphrase. I have also set the machine to auto lock after 5 minutes and always require a password on wake.</p>

<h2 id="hardening-ubuntu"><a id="harden"></a>hardening ubuntu</h2>

<p>There’s not actually loads required when looking to harden Ubuntu. The OS is mature and Canonical offer good transparency on <a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/livepatch">CVE reporting</a>.</p>

<h3 id="enable-livepatch"><a id="livepatch"></a>enable livepatch</h3>

<p>Ubuntu 20.04 prompts on first launch to enable <a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/livepatch">livepatch</a>. The elevator pitch is fairly simple: allow automatic critical kernel patching without the need for a restart.</p>

<h3 id="check-for-updates"><a id="updates"></a>check for updates</h3>

<p>Even if you enabled network updates during install, this is just good practice. Either use the auto updates if prompted, or head to terminal:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>apt update &amp; <span class="nb">sudo </span>apt upgrade</code></pre></figure>

<h3 id="remove-avahi"><a id="avahi"></a>remove avahi</h3>

<p>The <a href="http://manpages.ubuntu.com/manpages/bionic/man8/avahi-daemon.8.html">Avahi Daemon</a> implements Apple’s Rendevous/Bonjour. 👾<a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2011-1002">CVE-2011-1002</a> demonstrates the relative ease for bad actors to find vulnerabilities in the protocol, though it references Avahi &lt;0.6.29. Ubuntu 20.04 LTS ships with avahi-daemon_0.7-3.1, however, I don’t plan on using any hook-ups between this device and any Apple products so it may as well be purged.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>apt purge avahi-daemon</code></pre></figure>

<h3 id="make-like-madagascar"><a id="madagascar"></a>make like madagascar</h3>

<p><img src="/static/images/ubuntu-hardening-shut-down-everything.png" alt="shut. down. everything." /></p>

<p>Any idiot with a laptop and a follow-along “hacker guide” from Mr Robot could try setting up a reverse shell or find an open port to get up to no good. Hell, there’s in production industry standard software I am aware of which will crash if a certain port is sniffed. Uncomplicated Firewall (UFW) provides an iptables front-end and an easy way to manage firewall rules and work on an exception-only basis.</p>

<h4 id="deny-all-inbound-and-outbound-connections"><a id="ufwdeny"></a>deny all inbound and outbound connections</h4>

<p>First, enable UFW:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw <span class="nb">enable

</span>Firewall is active and enabled on system startup</code></pre></figure>

<p>Deny incoming connections:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw default deny incoming</code></pre></figure>

<p>Now forward connections:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw default deny forwarding</code></pre></figure>

<p>And finally, outgoing connections (all internet access will be blocked from this point):</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw default deny outgoing</code></pre></figure>

<h3 id="find-your-ufwinterface"><a id="ufwinterface"></a>find your ufwinterface</h3>

<p>To allow outgoing connections, you will need to reference your network adapter’s name. This is easy enough:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span>ip a

2: wlo1: &lt;BROADCAST,MULTICAST,UP,LOWER_UP&gt; mtu 1500 qdisc noqueue state UP group default qlen 1000
    <span class="nb">link</span>/ether aa:bb:cc:dd:ee:ff brd ff:ff:ff:ff:ff:ff
    altname wlp2s0
    inet 192.168.1.14/24 brd 192.168.1.255 scope global dynamic noprefixroute wlo1</code></pre></figure>

<h3 id="create-firewall-exceptions-and-allow-force-external-dns"><a id="ufwexceptions"></a>create firewall exceptions and <del>allow</del> force external dns</h3>

<p>Allow DNS, HTTP, and HTTPS traffic out over your chosen interface:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw allow out on wlo1 to 9.9.9.9 proto udp port 53 comment <span class="s1">'allow DNS on wlo1 ipv4'</span>
<span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw allow out on wlo1 to 2620:fe::fe proto udp port 53 comment <span class="s1">'allow DNS on wlo1 ipv6'</span>
<span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw allow out on wlo1 to any proto tcp port 80 comment <span class="s1">'allow HTTP on wlo1'</span>
<span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw allow out on wlo1 to any proto tcp port 443 comment <span class="s1">'allow HTTPS on wlo1'</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>After setting these rules, make sure you add the external DNS settings to your network interface device:</p>

<p><img src="/static/images/ubuntu-hardening-dns.png" alt="screenshot of dns settings panel in ubuntu" /></p>

<p>If these rules are blocking too much, allow all outgoing packets again:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">sudo </span>ufw default allow outgoing</code></pre></figure>

<h3 id="monitor-firewall-logs"><a id="ufwlogs"></a>monitor firewall logs</h3>

<p>To debug incoming or outgoing connections, use tail with the -f arg:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">tail</span> <span class="nt">-f</span> /var/log/ufw.log</code></pre></figure>

<p>You can use this to identify the IP, protocol, and port of any blocked connections and allow them where needed. Where IPs are fixed (with Quad9, for example) you can allow outbound connections to specific IPs and ports. Where IPs float, however, you may want to consider opening the port to all; keep in mind this approach increases your surface area to attackers.</p>

<h2 id="next-steps-and-todo"><a id="todo"></a>next steps and todo</h2>

<p>This is where I leave you. You should now have a decently working, hardened, Ubuntu 20.04 LTS persistant USB stick. You can treat it like a normal OS running on your machine. Below are some considerations and things you can do to check your understanding of what we’ve been through:</p>

<ul>
  <li>look at improving USB performance, investigate noatime (stackoverflow has some good discussions on this)</li>
  <li>regularly check your firewall logs. What else is being blocked?</li>
  <li>install some apps, like Spotify or Atom</li>
  <li>consider browser security. Look into plugins for FireFox and make sure to set Duck Duck Go as your default browser</li>
  <li>pen test this machine from a Kali Linux box</li>
  <li>use a password manager (<em>that one’s just in general, not just for this</em>)</li>
  <li>look at running through a VPN (<em>remember you’ll need to set firewall exceptions for that!</em>)</li>
</ul>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>setting up a dev environment for github pages ⌨️</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/tech/2021/04/05/github-pages-dev-environment-mac/"/>
   <updated>2021-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/tech/2021/04/05/github-pages-dev-environment-mac</id>
    <content type="html"><p>I’m hoping that sharing this will save somebody else the same headaches I went through trying to get a dev environment set up for GitHub pages on a Mac.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="table-of-contents">table of contents</h2>

<ol>
  <li><a href="#ruby">updating ruby</a></li>
  <li><a href="#bundle">installing bundler</a></li>
  <li><a href="#git">pulling your repo</a></li>
  <li><a href="#build">building the environment</a></li>
  <li><a href="#serve">serve –watch</a></li>
  <li><a href="#updates">further info and updates</a></li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h2 id="updating-ruby"><a id="ruby"></a>updating ruby</h2>

<p>Your first step is to update the version of Ruby installed by default to the currently supported version by GitHub Pages (<em>see ‘further info and updates’</em>).</p>

<p>Open terminal and run:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span>rvm <span class="nb">install </span>ruby-2.7.1</code></pre></figure>

<p>replacing the version number where appropriate.</p>

<p>This install can be fairly needy, so keep by it while it asks you for your sudo password and permission every 20 seconds or so. This step is limited by your processing power and internet connection, and can take a while.</p>

<p>Once complete, use:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span>ruby <span class="nt">-v</span>

ruby 2.7.1p83 <span class="o">(</span>2020-03-31 revision a0c7c23c9c<span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">[</span>x86_64-darwin19]</code></pre></figure>

<p>to confirm the install has set your new version as the default for the rvm. If not, use:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span>rvm <span class="nt">--default</span> use 2.7.1</code></pre></figure>

<h2 id="installing-bundler"><a id="bundler"></a>installing bundler</h2>

<p><a href="//bundler.io">Bundler</a> is recommended to install and run Jekyll on your local machine. Bundler manages all of your gem dependencies, and mirrors the build environment used by GitHub.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span>gem <span class="nb">install </span>bundler</code></pre></figure>

<h2 id="pulling-your-repo"><a id="git"></a>pulling your repo</h2>

<p>Now we’re cooking with gas. Pull your repo using your method of choice. The easiest way is to download the GitHub app for Mac and pull your Pages repo. You can also use CLI/SSH/GH-CLI (no judgement zone).</p>

<h2 id="building-the-environment"><a id="build"></a>building the environment</h2>

<p>Come back to Terminal and navigate to the root directory of your site.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span>bundle <span class="nb">install</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>If you receive any build errors at this point, check your Ruby version. If this matches what’s in this article, check ‘further info and updates’ just in case the version requirements have changed.</p>

<h2 id="serve-watch"><a id="serve"></a>serve –watch</h2>

<p>Now you can run your Jekyll site locally, and edit ‘til your hearts content. I use the –watch argument as it means I can continue to edit the site and changes will be picked up on the fly. Page builds are, again, limited by your machine. I say this as I recall being able to build my site in &lt;0.4 seconds on my old PC build, but it now takes around 7-8 seconds on the MacBook.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">$ </span>bundle <span class="nb">exec </span>jekyll serve <span class="nt">--watch</span></code></pre></figure>

<p><img src="/static/images/github-pages-dev-environment-mac.png" alt="screenshot of mid 2010 macbook editing this post" /></p>

<h2 id="further-info-and-updates"><a id="updates"></a>further info and updates</h2>

<ul>
  <li>The official GitHub Pages dependancies versions are found <a href="//pages.github.com/versions">here</a>. If you are using Bundler, the first thing to check is your Ruby version</li>
  <li>If your version of github-pages or the other dependancies slip out of date on your local machine, you need to update them using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bundle update github-pages</code></li>
</ul>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>life update 👶</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2019/06/24/life-update/"/>
   <updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2019/06/24/life-update</id>
    <content type="html"><h3 id="its-been-a-while-since-i-posted-on-this-blog-in-between-then-and-now-i-had-another-website-which-i-didnt-renew-and-i-forgot-to-backup-the-posts-so-go-me">it’s been a while since i posted on this blog, in between then and now i had another website which i didn’t renew and i forgot to backup the posts, so go me</h3>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/yQZEeaAl.png" alt="Detective Pikachu" /></p>

<p>I have unashamedly neglected this blog since the 28th January 2018, and
 invariably I am a monster.</p>

<p>Here are some things that have happened in my life since I last posted, I:</p>

<ul>
  <li>got a new job to try working in IT</li>
  <li>learned (some) C++</li>
  <li>sold all of my Apple products and switched to a Google Pixel 3</li>
  <li>moved into a house</li>
  <li>got another new job working in IT</li>
  <li>enjoyed the <strong>shit</strong> out of <em>Detective Pikachu</em> (the movie and the DS game)</li>
  <li>forgot to cancel the free Spotify trial that came with my PS4 but stuck with it</li>
  <li>signed up for an unlimited travel card to get discount public transport through work</li>
  <li>(tried to) got over myself</li>
  <li><strong>had a baby</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>Niamh Imogen is 10 weeks old and she is my absolute world. I joked for a while
 that I wouldn’t dare bring a child into this world in the state that it’s in;
 but at the same time I’m nearly 30 and everything just kind of fell
 into place with the love of my life. I don’t think I can change the world or
 save anyone or anything, but I can try to be the best version of myself to
 give her the best possible chance. Plus: now I have someone to look after me
 when I’m in a care home.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>my new typewriter - the powerbook g4 🍎</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2018/01/25/powerbook-g4/"/>
   <updated>2018-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2018/01/25/powerbook-g4</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="700" height="394" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/gA-NDZb29I4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="0"> </iframe>

<h2 id="in-2003-steve-jobs-introduced-the-15-powerbook-series-of-notebooks-to-the-world-a-year-later-he-sandwiched-the-15-machine-in-between-12-and-17-counterparts-13-years-later-i-bought-a-12-powerbook-g4-why-how-what-and-most-importantly-why">In 2003, Steve Jobs introduced the 15” PowerBook series of notebooks to the world. A year later, he sandwiched the 15” machine in between 12” and 17” counterparts. 13 years later, I bought a 12” PowerBook G4. Why? How? What? And, most importantly, why?</h2>

<hr />

<p>As a kid I hated Apple products. Actually, let me be honest, I hated rich people. Apple products seemed to be unnecessarily expensive to myself and, although I would watch the Keynotes and very much want the products on offer, I resented the products for never being able to afford them.
Flash forward to 2014, I got a full time job. With a full time job came an income, with an income came spending. At first: an iPhone; then came an iPad, eventually I moved onto a MacBook Air, then a MacBook Pro, an Apple Watch and finally the AirPods. I am fully indoctrinated into the Church of Jobs. I fucking love it.</p>

<h2 id="obsolescence-drives-productivity">obsolescence drives productivity</h2>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/VboWv6Q.jpg" alt="PowerBook G4 12 inch" /></p>

<p>My biggest issue when completing any task is procrastination. Essay? Xbox. Research? League of Legends. I find that if I can do something else, I generally will, this blog was actually once of my procrastinatory efforts throughout education. Therein lies the problem. My work rarely requires me to take anything home, which means I no longer need to procrastinate anything beyond laundry or cooking or food shopping, all tasks which (for now) have a novelty and an allure. This means (probably noticeably) this blog has been neglected, as have my other previously procrastination driven hobbies such as PC gaming and programming. What this means is when I do actually want to complete tasks like OC gaming or programming or writing for this blog; I procrastinate it. We’ve reached meta-crastination, people.</p>

<p>What the rant above is trying to justify is my need for a device I can complete a single task on at a time with, that cannot be used for anything beyond basic writing/browsing, in some sort of attempt to force myself to write and code.
I flirted with the idea of returning to the OG Google Chromebook (link to review here), however the forced-always-up-to-date software had driven it beyond the point of no return for obsolescence. The “only-web” system had fallen to the web, JavaScript and multi-meg pages had finally surpassed the already-close-to limitations Atom processor. So I decided to go deeper–more vintage, more abandoned. Enter the PowerBook G4.</p>

<p>With 768 MB of RAM and a 1 GHz PowerPC G4 processor, the PowerBook G4 was just what I needed for single-tasking computing that cannot take me beyond the means of word processing and 2006-era web browsing. Armed with a copy of iWork 2006 and the Internet Radio (college radio at that) of iTunes 10.5.6–which not only still works, but works better than iTunes for Windows ever have/will/could–I’ve been able to return to writing and coding.</p>

<h2 id="but-tom-dont-you-have-an-ipad-pro-a-macbook-pro-and-several-notebooks-for-all-this-shit">but tom, don’t you have an ipad pro, a macbook pro, and several notebooks for all this shit?</h2>

<p>Yes, yes I do. But this thing cost me £50 and I fucking love it. After nearly breaking the damn thing to upgrade the 4200 RPM/40 GB stock HDD to a 5600 RPM/160 GB HDD and loading a fresh eBay copy of Leopard onto the thing, I’m finding myself able to sit with the PowerBook on a coffee table whilst I bash out some writing. The MbPro still gets love when I need to do some light gaming or actual productive coding, and the iPad Pro is now a work device I use for one to ones and documenting coaching. The PowerBook has well and truly found a niche in my tech-life.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ipad pro: the least ipad ipad yet 💻</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/12/17/ipad-pro/"/>
   <updated>2017-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/12/17/ipad-pro</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="700" height="394" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/RwaYflHAIGQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="0"> </iframe>

<h2 id="the-ipad-has-been-around-for-the-longest-time-now-even-longer-if-you-believe-it-started-life-as-what-the-iphone-turned-into-apple-has-revised-and-retuned-its-glorified-giant-ipod-touch-time-and-time-again-and-nowfully-indoctrined-into-the-ways-of-appleive-jumped-into-the-fray-but-can-this-device-truly-hit-the-mark-as-a-pro-device">The iPad has been around for the longest time now, even longer if you believe it started life as what the iPhone turned into. Apple has revised and retuned it’s glorified giant iPod touch time and time again, and now—fully indoctrined into the ways of Apple—I’ve jumped into the fray. But can this device truly hit the mark as a “Pro” device?</h2>

<hr />

<p>I’ve been using the new iPad Pro as my daily driver for just over 48 hours now, but I don’t feel like I’m using an iPad—and I think that’s Apple’s intention.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/sQB2NjhJHvY">iPad Pro — What’s a computer — Apple</a></p>

<p>Whilst I don’t see myself being so… forceful with this over £600 piece of equipment (though I’ve totally nailed the fold slam trick) I can completely understand Apple’s logic on the direction they’ve taken with their Pro device. The iPad is for people who want a couch computer, a device they can watch YouTube and browse the web on. The Pro takes that concept and blurs the line further between itself and a laptop. The Pro sports Apple’s new custom built A10X chip, which drives a beautiful Retina display and up to 120Hz refresh rates (which seems to be supported on everything from <em>Hearthstone</em> to the Home Screen). The result of this is a snappy, gorgeous machine which feels as premium as its’ cost demands. Of course, this is only half the story. In previous iterations of iPad, the device has only been as good as the giant iPhone software it’s running. Enter iOS 11.</p>

<h2 id="macos-meets-ios-meets-macos">macos meets ios meets macos</h2>
<p>Users of the Mac will know that over the past couple of versions of the OS, the gap between iOS and MacOS has been shrinking (hello Siri). I almost consider Yosemite the practice-version of what would become iOS 11 with it’s Windows 7 snap-style take on multitasking and it’s obsession with full screen. I will admit on the 13” MacBook Pro, and indeed on larger screens, full screen computing frustrates me; I do consider myself a “Windows” user (in the sense that I like to have lots going on with my screen at once),  but the iPad, with iOS 11, finally obliges my hardstuck ways.</p>

<p>The new operating system feels fluid and intuitive, and apps snap freely between iPad versions (in 50-100% size) and iPhone versions (at less than 50% size), leaving you able to do crazy things, like watching a YouTube video and reading BBC News at the same time. 2017 is crazy.</p>

<h2 id="accessories-are-power">accessories are power</h2>
<p>The iPad Pro carries much more than a shiny OS and multitasking, it is also backed by exclusive accessories. One of said accessories makes complete sense to me and I feel should be included with the device. The other is a £99 stylus.</p>

<p>The iPad Pro Smart Keyboard is small, discreet, and doubles as a stand for when you don’t want to type and just want to watch/play. The key travel is shallow and does take getting used it, but it carries a tactile feel and I’ve been able to get up to full-speed typing within a few hours of using it. The keyboard supports all the usual array of shortcuts fresh from the Mac, including <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd+tab</code> (iOS now sports a cute task switched) and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd+h</code> to go to the home screen. Where the struggle begins is more to do with what I’m used to. I’m missing my 7” slab of glass underneath the space bar that lets me point to things on my screen<sup><a href="#footnotes/pointing">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The Apple Pencil is difficult. In theory I feel like it makes complete sense. The pencil is to the iPad Pro what the Smart Keyboard is to the iPad Pro. One lets you write away and pro-user-shortcut your way around the device, and seems the perfect match for writers; the other is a pencil. And I guess the pencil carries with it the ability to draw, and point with greater accuracy, or colour, or stencil, or whatever, but for me it’s come as an expensive “also this”. I’m not saying there’s anything inherently <em>wrong</em> with the thing—it feels weighted in your hand and is precise <em>af</em>—rather, it just doesn’t feel like it holds a true… use for me. I have, however, still found myself reaching for it instead of pointing with my finger whilst using the Smart Keyboard, as it bridges the gap quite nicely and leaves me not having to lean in to point.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/DnGmAzf.jpg" alt="iPad with Pencil and Smart Keyboard" /></p>

<h2 id="so-who-is-this-for">so who is this for?</h2>
<p>The iPad Pro sits on the forefront of what can only be described as a two-pronged niche. On one hand are the professionals who needs a solid, reliable, tablet to draw on or write with. iOS has really matured over the years and the operating system can finally comfortably support a power user with their “lighter” tasks, and almost all apps from the App Store support some kind of hand off to a fully fledged power app on the Mac proper. On the other hand, the iPad Pro sits in a rather new market; the “Pro Consumer”. Some people (particularly me… and probably other nerds) need a device that is light enough and good enough to run YouTube, Music, and a couple of games without choking; but also heavy-duty enough to keep up, multitask, and carry through an entire day without a charge<sup><a href="#footnotes/battery-life">2</a></sup>. I think Apple has truly reimagined what the word “Pro” means in it’s Pro line, and I don’t think it’s short for Professional anymore.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">conclusion</h2>
<p>The iPad Pro presents itself as a Microsoft Surface killer, but I think Apple missed the mark there. What I really see the iPad Pro as is a MacBook Air killer. This device is exactly what I wanted in Uni, and to be honest it fits my niche quite well. If you’re anything like me and you need a “Pro by 2017’s Pro” device, I’d recommend buying the shit outta this device. For anyone else, I think a trip to the Apple Store to just have a play with the thing would soon swing you into the former category.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/nt9kry8.jpg" alt="iPad with Tom" />
(“What’s a computer?” — Whilst I find it completely obnoxious when taken literally, I totally get where the marketing department was coming from with that line… sorry)</p>
<hr />
<p><a name="footnotes/pointing">1</a>: The touch screen on the iPad is incredibly responsive, 20ms to be precise, however there is a learning curve for keyboard and mouse diehards such as myself to learn to reach out and touch rather than using a secondary device.</p>

<p><a name="footnotes/battery-life">2</a>: Apple has claimed 10 hours on devices before and been very, very wrong (and have stung me for that, thanks man). So far the iPad Pro seems to live true to the 10 hour claim, though I’d be silly to bet against that changing after more battery cycles.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>you should watch the digimon movie 📽</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/08/30/you-should-watch-the-digimon-movie/"/>
   <updated>2017-08-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/08/30/you-should-watch-the-digimon-movie</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="700" height="394" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/iTwlf5u4c9g" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="0"> </iframe>

<h3 id="why-dont-they-just-always-immediately-digivolve-to-the-max-level">“Why don’t they just always immediately Digivolve to the max level?”</h3>

<hr />
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>fizzbuzz 💻</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/08/08/fizzbuzz/"/>
   <updated>2017-08-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/08/08/fizzbuzz</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="700" height="394" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/MKQDzpIwAMo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="0"> </iframe>

<h3 id="im-trying-to-learn-apples-swift-programming-language-the-only-way-i-know-how-to-learn-a-programming-languageby-smacking-a-keyboard-with-my-fingers-until-something-works">I’m trying to learn Apple’s Swift programming language the only way I know how to learn a programming language–by smacking a keyboard with my fingers until something works.</h3>

<hr />

<p>I completed A-level Computing back in college which taught me a couple of valuable lessons:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>VB.NET is a cruel mistress, but Stockholm Syndrome has me only remembering the good times</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It’s not about being able to program; it’s about being able to problem solve</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’ve seen quite a few people online raving about Swift (particularly the videos Apple uploaded showing everyone from babies to grandparents writing apps in Swift) and had some spare hours between work, sleep, and <em>Crash Bandicoot</em>; so I’ve started to try pick up Swift to see what I can accomplish.</p>

<p>Apple has a fantastic free eBook they keep updated for learning the basics of Swift as well as a website they maintain with a primer as well as a PHP.net style function breakdown. It goes without saying that documentation is king.</p>

<h2 id="so-wtf-is-fizzbuzz">so wtf is fizzbuzz</h2>

<p>FizzBuzz is a children’s game which some companies use in interviews when hiring programmers.</p>

<p>FizzBuzz is a game where two people take turns reciting numbers from 1-100 (or higher). If a number is a multiple of 3 the person must say “Fizz” instead, if a number is a multiple of 5: “Buzz”, and for both “FizzBuzz”. For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>1</li>
  <li>2</li>
  <li>fizz</li>
  <li>3</li>
  <li>buzz</li>
  <li>fizz</li>
  <li>7</li>
  <li>8</li>
  <li>fizz</li>
  <li>buzz</li>
  <li>11</li>
  <li>fizz</li>
  <li>13</li>
  <li>14</li>
  <li>fizzbuzz</li>
</ul>

<p>Asking a programmer to reproduce this should be a very easy task, but it does also provide a great insight into what style of programmer they are. Do they slap shit together and hope for the best? Or do they actually think of edge cases and future-proofing?</p>

<p>There’s tonnes of great resources online on FizzBuzz, including <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QPZ0pIK_wsc">this video</a> by Tom Scott on the various methods people use to solve FizzBuzz. My method is below, in Swift.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-swift" data-lang="swift"><span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">...</span><span class="mi">100</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">var</span> <span class="nv">output</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s">""</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="mi">3</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">0</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">output</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="s">"Fizz"</span> <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="mi">5</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">0</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">output</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="s">"Buzz"</span> <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">output</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="s">""</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">output</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kt">String</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">output</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>And here’s the output:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/moQqpet.png" alt="fizzbuzz" /></p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>half time 👟</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/07/30/half-time/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/07/30/half-time</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="700" height="394" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/J3TjDUnlclk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="0"> </iframe>

<h3 id="sorry-about-the-lack-of-updates-blog-theres-been-a-few-times-this-year-ive-half-started-a-post-and-then-just-kind-of-left-itand-thats-okay-heres-some-of-my-accomplishments-so-far-this-year-suck-it-2017">Sorry about the lack of updates, blog. There’s been a few times this year I’ve half-started a post and then just kind of left it–and that’s okay! Here’s some of my accomplishments so far this year. (<em>Suck it, 2017</em>)</h3>

<hr />

<p>Time flies.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the year <a href="/2017/01/01/my-annual-year">I looked back at 2016</a> and took stock on what had been happening so far (TL;DR: time moves pretty quick). Flash forward to July and I’ve realised I have neglected this blog. I also realised that doesn’t really matter.</p>

<h2 id="reflection-is-a-powerful-tool">reflection is a powerful tool</h2>

<p>In January I took a lot of time reflecting before writing my post, this was a very powerful thing to do. For one: it put a lot of things into perspective; huge problems seemed tiny in hindsight, secondly, it allowed me to put a lot of what I’d done into words–and that had a really huge impact. Sometimes accomplishments are drowned out by the problems of the time, problems that seem insignificant in the long run.</p>

<p>2017 has been a very good year so far. Don’t get me wrong, there’s been the usual fair share of good days and shit days, but I’m finally starting to maintain a sense of purpose through it all (25 years late, mind).</p>

<h2 id="i-am-still-in-love-with-snapchat">i am still in love with snapchat</h2>

<p>I mentioned last time that I had managed to shake my perpetual social network anxiety, scrolling back through Photos.app shows that hasn’t changed. This has the benefit of me being able to take small amounts of time just scroll through my photos and reminisce over when stuff goes right.</p>

<h2 id="promises-promises">promises promises</h2>

<p>Gonna try to update this blog a little more regularly for the rest of the year. I also want to have a go at a video of some kind (waiting on Josh to let me use his drone). Also, I got an Apple Watch… I’m sorry.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>my annual year 📖</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/01/01/my-annual-year/"/>
   <updated>2017-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2017/01/01/my-annual-year</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="700" height="394" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/Lm-rpaWkONI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="0"> </iframe>

<p>I sit on a new bed in the same room wearing my second ever pair of joggers typing on a new MacBook Pro after drinking a bottle of Cava to myself. But how did I get here? In <em>The Onion</em> fashion, this is: “<strong>my annual year</strong>”.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="2016-the-year-of-did-i-do-that">2016: the year of “did <em>I</em> do that?”</h2>

<p>My greatest accomplishment in 2016 stood on the shoulders of my second-greatest: I became a manager at <em>big red</em>. I was voted “People’s Choice” for best Customer Service Team Leader/Adviser. Now, I’m not the work obsessed gremlin ranking such an achievement would suggest, but it was the moment I accepted what I meant to others. I saw my best friend cry as I took the prize and felt like I’d really done them proud, in fact, I’d done <em>myself</em> proud.</p>

<h2 id="my-biggest-change-i-lost-my-socialnetworkanxiety">my biggest change: I lost my social(<em>network</em>)anxiety</h2>

<p><img src="http://s23.postimg.org/b8n1j2msb/IMG_0194.jpg" alt="london trip photo" width="200px" style="float:left; padding-right: 10px;" /></p>

<p>2016 was the first year I actually enjoyed public social networks. From Twitter to SnapChat and Instagram and back I actually enjoyed sharing my life on social networks. Actually, no, I wasn’t hung up on exactly what I was sharing anymore because I was just sharing snippets of my life. I think that’s kinda the point though, so go me for finally getting it?</p>

<p>I just spent 20 minutes or so reviewing Photos on the MacBook (which, by the way, is fucking seamless) and it reminded me of how much I’ve actually done this year, and more surprisingly, how much I’ve actually documented. Fuck, I’ve even taken <em>selfies</em>.</p>

<h2 id="speaking-of-selfies">speaking of selfies…</h2>

<p><img src="https://s23.postimg.org/hnm2fqti3/IMG_0289.jpg" alt="selfie" width="200px" style="float:right; padding-left: 10px;" /></p>

<p>I seemed to finally, after 24 years, crack the answer to the age-old question of “how do you want it?” when going to the barbers. In doing that (and after receiving at least <em>one</em> compliment) I’ve found myself taking much more pictures of my face. Until tonight I really didn’t appreciate how useful that actually is, as it’s enabled me to take stock on a lot of positives this year (<em>right: German Christmas market with Alex</em>). On a serious note, it’s really shown how much my confidence has improved this year on the whole–for one I’m now leading a team of 12 people which requires a lot of public speaking, which I’m unashamedly loving!</p>

<h2 id="other-memories-in-no-particular-order">other memories (in no particular order)</h2>

<ul>
  <li>traded in the MacBook Air for a 2016 MacBook Pro (review coming soon?)</li>
  <li>spent annual leave away from home - <strong>alone</strong>!</li>
  <li>travelled to London for a spontaneous day</li>
  <li><em>Uncharted 4</em></li>
  <li>felt financial stability</li>
  <li>reached 10 stone, officially making me a “healthy weight” for my height</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="oh-and-i-saw-these-two-kittens-all-grown-up">oh and I saw these two kittens all grown up</h2>

<p><img src="https://s23.postimg.org/jgoz42eor/IMG_0546.jpg" alt="kitties!" /></p>

<p>Happy New Year &lt;3</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>quick and lazy random titles 💻</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/snippet/2016/11/06/quick-and-lazy-random-titles/"/>
   <updated>2016-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/snippet/2016/11/06/quick-and-lazy-random-titles</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="700" height="394" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/MVRg8gZ8zPA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="0"> </iframe>

<h2 id="redesigned">redesigned</h2>

<p>Just to add some context to this: I refreshed the blog design <em>again</em>, and in part with stealing every idea I come across I’ve made a really quick and dirty random tagline picker thing. For a demo, refresh this page a few times.</p>

<h2 id="step-one-create-an-array">step one: create an array</h2>

<p>Something as quick and dirty as I’m making here needs a dirty and quick array:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-js" data-lang="js"><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">tags</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">Registered CSS offender.</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">Mum, I</span><span class="se">\'</span><span class="s1">m on the Internet!</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">#implications</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">Powered by magic beans</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">Brought to you by Caprisuns</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">A new design every week or your money back</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">Come on, grab your friends!</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">Follow me on Twitter!</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">Steamed hams</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">My other blog gets updates</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">&lt;i&gt;"lol"&lt;/i&gt; - you</span><span class="dl">'</span>
<span class="p">];</span></code></pre></figure>

<h2 id="step-two-pseudorandom-number-generator">step two: pseudorandom number generator</h2>

<p>Anyone who’s ever done “randomness” in computer programming before knows the general formula <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">random() * (max - min + 1)) + min</code> (where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">random()</code> generally gives a number between 0 and 1). I won’t pretend to understand or remember how this works, however if you’re interested in the how check <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/1527820">this excellent explanation</a> on StackOverflow out.</p>

<p>Now since our array starts at 0 (so we have no min), our next–and only other–line can just be:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-js" data-lang="js"><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">random_tag</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">tags</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">round</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">random</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">tags</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">))];</span></code></pre></figure>

<h2 id="step-three-its-lit">step three: it’s lit</h2>

<p>Throw in a cheeky tag into where you want your random tag:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-html" data-lang="html"><span class="nt">&lt;span</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">random-tag</span><span class="nt">&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>then add a not so cheeky <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">document.addEventListener</code> to insert <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">random_tag</code> into your page:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-js" data-lang="js"><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">addEventListener</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">DOMContentLoaded</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">event</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">getElementById</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">random-tag</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">innerHTML</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2"> </span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">random_tag</span>
<span class="p">})</span></code></pre></figure>

<h2 id="theres-probably-a-better-way-to-do-this">there’s probably a better way to do this</h2>

<p>Full disclosure: I generally have no idea what I’m doing, so if you know of or find a better way of performing this fairly simple task: go ahead and use it.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>organisation 📕</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2016/08/09/organisation/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2016/08/09/organisation</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="740" height="416" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/PT2_F-1esPk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="0"> </iframe>

<p>So yeah, I got the job.</p>

<h2 id="deep-end-">deep end 🌊</h2>

<p>After a full week managing I think I can safely say I will never think I know everything in a job role ever again. All internal (<em>and external</em>) panicking aside, I bought myself a Moleskine diary and a journal, in a thinly veiled attempt to look organised.</p>

<h2 id="prioritising">prioritising</h2>

<p>I find now that if I don’t tackle more tasks than I have set, I’m going to feel like I had an unproductive day. Sometimes this will happen, however what I’ve tried to do is always make sure I have three tasks that I will focus on; it could be a specific objective or a broad task, but as long as I can say I tackled my three priorities I can say I’ve at least had a productive day.</p>

<h2 id="day-planning">day planning</h2>

<p>I take around twenty minutes per day laying out how I would like my day to go. This is done by writing down every task I can think of in any order. I then mark important tasks with a *, tasks that <strong>need</strong> doing with a !, tasks that require research with a 🔎 and tasks that can be delegated with →. As the day progresses I can mark tasks started with a ⚫️ and tick off completed items.</p>

<h2 id="meetings">meetings</h2>

<p>Meetings are inevitable, but it’s a good idea to pen them in. Having something pop up in Outlook is also good, but for the times I’m not at my computer it’s good to just pop open the book and see what I have coming up.</p>

<h2 id="workbasket">workbasket</h2>

<p>Something I added after having a chat with another manager is a “workbasket”, it’s a view of how I feel my time has been spent on any given day. I break the day down into its seven working hours, and give each block a code as to what I feel I was spending most of my time doing, be it meetings, management, coaching or feedback. There’s no perfect balance of activities and not every day will feature every task, but it gives me an idea of how I’m spending my time; plus it gives me a heads up as to why I might be getting behind on a task (for example, if my observations are behind, maybe I should be spending more time doing feedback or coaching).</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/VMWX2OPm.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>For the diary I cut out one of the Author of the Weeks from the <a href="http://moleskine.com/template">MSK/template</a> website.</p>

<h2 id="u-do-u">u do u</h2>

<p>All this said and done, I think everyone will find their own magic super secret way to organise themselves. I think the biggest thing to focus on isn’t anything to do with organisation or making sure you act the part; it’s asking for help. Attaching to as many people who have been in your position to find what you need to do and how you can do it can be the difference between whether you succeed or fail, because at this stage tasks are rarely delegated from above.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>switching gears, or how i accidentally stumbled my way into the fray of a management job contest 🏆</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/ramble/2016/07/16/shifting-gears/"/>
   <updated>2016-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/ramble/2016/07/16/shifting-gears</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="740" height="416" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/LVltnKhb_vo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>As I alluded to in a previous rant, I have the unnatural talent of allowing myself into slumping. By this I mean I can be quite content in the art of settling. I’m coming up to the two-year mark at <em>big red bank</em>, and until very recently I was reaching a similar position I was in this time last year: complacency.</p>

<p>In my last month’s career conversation my manager hit the nail on the head; I am happy to silently pay my dues, get on with the work and take no recognition for it. I hit &gt;90% of my performance indicators, I cause little to no drama and I don’t like to draw any attention to myself. She continued that she fears I will become bored in my role, so she offered I become an SME in a new focus for the bank: digital opportunities, in order to give me something new to do. Alongside this she suggested I keep an open mind about “progression”, to which I agreed. Later that day I applied for a manager job. Not even four days later I’m told I have a preliminary interview on Monday.</p>

<p>I don’t necessarily think I’ll even pass the prelim stage, hell I’m surprised my <cite>written in thirty minutes oh Dog I sent it before even proof-reading it</cite> cover letter even got me this far; but so far my Saturday has been spent swatting up on policies and procedures a manager undertakes ready for a roleplay and a presentation. Oh boy.</p>

<h2 id="so-what-else-is-new">so what else is new?</h2>

<p>I bought myself a Ducky One keyboard, partly because I quite fancy taking up writing (be it notes, blogs, reviews, stories I’ll never publish) and the Ducky is renowned for being a delight to type on—which it is—but also because CLACK CLACK. The sound of a fully mechanical, cherry switched keyboard is just downright… pleasurable to type on (see attached YouTube video for evidence).</p>

<iframe width="740" height="416" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/BhWac4ksHss" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<blockquote>
  <p>CLACK CLACK</p>
</blockquote>

<p>After a few months of owning a PS4 and a PS Vita I’ve established a fairly healthy amount of games to play through. I recently completed played through <em>Uncharted 4, Until Dawn, Ratchet and Clank, Rogue Warrior, Hyper Light Drifter, NBA 2k16</em> and <em>The Last of Us</em>, thanks to PlayStation Plus however, the list doesn’t go down at any scary speed. I still have <em>Dragon Age, Uncharted: Golden Abyss, Gravity Falls, Life is Strange</em> and <em>Persona 4</em> to chug through, I might even hit this shit up with some notes or a review about them. All the while I’m mid-Gold on <em>League of Legends</em>, though with the shake up in the ranked queue system I really don’t know if I can get carried to Platinum again like last season, but y’know.</p>

<h2 id="so-whats-the-plan">so what’s the plan?</h2>

<p>Lawyer up, hit the gym, delete Facebook. Seriously though I have no idea, <em>voice in my head</em>, I can see myself going in a few different directions and to be honest I kind of like the idea of all of them. Hopefully I learn enough from failing my assessment on Monday to get a shoe onto the ladder, if not: I have things lined up still, I’m happy enough where I am, albeit I would love to move out (big up the rental market); but that takes money. Money I keep spending on Ducky keyboards and every games console going. Adulting is easy, right?</p>

<p>And oh yeah, <em>Pokémon Go</em> is a thing.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>hyper light drifter 🎮</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/game-review/2016/04/27/hyper-light-drifter/"/>
   <updated>2016-04-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/game-review/2016/04/27/hyper-light-drifter</id>
    <content type="html"><p>Having now dabbled in the <em>Souls</em> series I can say with certainty that I am a
masochist.</p>

<p>Hyper Light Drifter appeared on my Steam queue as a game it thought I would like
 (<em>as Steam does</em>). After reading the reviews and watching a couple of the
videos, I was sold. 30 minutes later I was hooked.</p>

<h2 id="okay-ill-try-one-more-time-then-im-going-to-bed">‘okay, i’ll try one more time then i’m going to bed’</h2>

<p>Hyper Light Drifter is a game about… well… I don’t really know. The only
backstory you get is from the odd cutscene which is backed by the game’s
incredible soundtrack. The cutscenes are not spoken. There are no subtitles.
The only ‘language’ is the odd grunt from NPCs. So far all I can tell is the PC
has some sort of illness that makes him periodically cough up blood, and some
friendly fella took him to a central city. From this central city you are free
to tackle the game in any direction you like. From what I have begun to gather
from the game the objective is to dungeon crawl four areas which piece together
four… things. These things seem to be the focal point of the game. I have
encountered a couple of NPCs who have tried to distract me with what looks
like optional boss rooms, but I’m not too sure yet (I’m only 30-40% through the
game).</p>

<p>The game’s central mechanic revolves around timing. This game is <em>fucking hard</em>.
You are given 5 hit points (which I am yet to find a way to increase), and the
game is lightly littered with HP boosters (which get you from any health to max).
But it’s not about hit points or healing–it’s about getting it fucking right.</p>

<div style="position:relative;padding-bottom:calc(100% / 1.78)"><iframe src="https://gfycat.com/ifr/DecisiveCrispAphid" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>

<p>The PC has three real moves (more if you collect the games rare ‘currency’).
A hack/slash, a gun which recharges bullets from hacking/slashing and your
bread and butter: a dash which can be used three times in quick succession.
Each game area usually has an exploration area, followed by some warm up creatures
unique to that area. Then there is a ‘boss room’ which throws everything at you
at once. After a succession of deaths you slowly learn the
area’s pattern, you change your style, you become more patient. You <em>become</em> a
ninja. This game does not allow a simple -run in hack slash spam A- approach, in
fact, it <em>punishes</em> it; and when you finally get that checkpoint and quadrant,
holy fuck does it feel rewarding.</p>

<h1 id="you-could-legit-gfycat-any-scene-in-this-game">you could legit gfycat any scene in this game</h1>

<p>This game is downright beautiful. It’s ambiance is created by the amazing
backdrop and colours, combined with it’s sombre soundtrack, which slowly builds
up from the melodic piano in the safe habour central city up to the rhythmic
dungeon crawling soundtrack (which really gets me in the zone). Occasionally
the game feels fairly <em>wtf</em>, particularly with it’s non-language cryptic
backstory and random blood-coughing moments, but on the whole Hyper Light Drifter
feels like a game that should cost more than it’s £15.99 price tag.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>thoughts on squarecms 🚀</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/03/25/thoughts-on-square/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2016/03/25/thoughts-on-square</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="650" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/W_rC-495Z_A" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>I’ve started working on SquareCMS again recently after having some time off work, the <a href="//github.com/tomchatting/square">GitHub</a> is being updated a lot more and there’s a working demo <a href="//square-shiftysu.rhcloud.com">here</a> if you want to have a play.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/CYyqyD7.png" alt="square admin" /></p>

<h2 id="so-will-i-go-back-to-running-on-square">so will i go back to running on square?</h2>

<p>Probably not, simply because I’m so used to running my blog as a git repo now, and I love GitHub flavoured markdown (which I’m probably going to build a plugin for Square anyway).</p>

<h2 id="so-why-do-it">so why do it?</h2>

<p>Because I actually want to, and I actually enjoy writing code again.</p>

<h2 id="so-whats-to-come-false-promises-time">so what’s to come? (false promises time)</h2>

<p>So at the moment I’m focusing on getting the thing working as it was before (over five years ago), but there <em>is</em> some stuff I want to work on adding:</p>

<ul>
  <li>full plugin support (the PDO should help here)</li>
  <li>shit tonnes better documentation</li>
  <li>multi-user support (although I’m not too sure on this one)</li>
  <li>ability to add custom tags without changing a line of code (thinking of how Jekyll handles custom tags in the layout of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> markdown files)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="when-will-20-drop-its-alpha-tag">when will 2.0 drop it’s alpha tag?</h2>

<p>Well, it’ll go beta when I’m ready, and it’ll go final when I’m ready too. So basically don’t hold your breath.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>quick and dirty referencing 🖊</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/02/23/quick-and-dirty-referencing/"/>
   <updated>2016-02-23T21:20:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2016/02/23/quick-and-dirty-referencing</id>
    <content type="html"><p>One lesson all uni students should have in their schedules every year is a
lecture from the librarian of their school. In my case that was a recently
graduated Humanities student (because who else would be the Sciences librarian?)
who would give us the same talk every year on the importance of referencing.</p>

<p>Though boring as hell, I didn’t realise how lucky I was to receive something like
this so consistently during my years at uni; it was only after I discovered
my sister was never taught to reference.</p>

<iframe width="650" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/XF3pG6DndYs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<h1 id="turn-it-in-and-you-and-the-devil-too">turn it in and you (and the devil, too!)</h1>

<p>All universities in this day and age use some sort of plagiarism ‘detecting’
tool such as turnitin to sort the cheats from the heroes. Most of these
are terrible, terrible pieces of pseudo-ware which simply plug your work
through Google et al to try and work out if you just copy-pasted Wikipedia.</p>

<p>To combat this, the primary school child in you will automatically begin
rewriting what you are copying into your own words, but this is where the basic
rule of academic writing steps in:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>if you write anything which cannot be considered your own thought or idea, it <strong>must</strong> be referenced (Chatting, 2016)</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="building-references">building references</h1>

<p>Wherever possible, you should compile a list of the sources you use for each
page of your writing (<em>just stick it in the footer</em>) so you can go back once
it’s finished so you can build your bibliography (which I’ll touch on later).</p>

<p>For books, grab the:</p>

<ul>
  <li>author’s name(s)</li>
  <li>year of publication</li>
  <li>book title</li>
  <li>edition (if not the 1st)</li>
  <li>city of publication</li>
  <li>publisher</li>
</ul>

<p>For journal articles, you’ll need the:</p>

<ul>
  <li>author’s name(s)</li>
  <li>year the journal was published</li>
  <li>title of the article</li>
  <li>title of the journal</li>
  <li>the page number or range of pages of the article</li>
  <li>volume and issue numbers where you can provide them</li>
</ul>

<p>For ‘electronic resources’, try to get the above plus the:</p>

<ul>
  <li>date you accessed the sources</li>
  <li>the URL or email</li>
  <li>type of resource (email, forum, website, etc)</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="quotes-vs-interpretation">quotes vs interpretation</h1>

<p>If you ever use the idea of another person or quote someone (which you should
keep to a bare minimum) you should be looking to add a reference. You can get
away with not using a reference <strong>only</strong> when the information can be considered
public domain, for example stating that the 6’o’clock News generally airs at 6pm.</p>

<h2 id="direct-quotes">direct quotes</h2>

<p>If you ever copy what an author says word-for-word, use inverted commas or
double inverted commas to wrap the phrase and follow it immediately with your
reference. Do not modify the sentence in anyway, leaving mistakes as they are.
You can correct any errors and show your reader you recognise them by using <em>(sic)</em>.</p>

<h2 id="referencing-interpretation">referencing interpretation</h2>

<p>This is how you should be completing the majority of your academic writing, as
it is a true display of your understanding of a topic. You must still reference
the ideas, and this is done by quoting the author’s surname and the year of
publication in brackets.</p>

<h1 id="referencing-the-actual-way-to-do-it">referencing (the actual way to do it)</h1>

<p>Harvard referencing can be broken down into two parts: the article’s body, and
the reference list.</p>

<p>The article body points at the reference list using the author’s surname and
date, which is then displayed in full with the source used in the reference
list, for example if I were to say: referencing is a fking ballache.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Chatting (2016) suggests referencing is a tedious process.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Summarises the gist of what I said, whereas a direct quote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Chatting (2016) stated ‘referencing is a fking(sic) ballache’</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Referencing a journal or book might look like this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>F. D. Martinez, 2007. “Genes, environments, development and asthma: a reappraisal” doi: 10.1183/​09031936.00087906ERJ January 1, 2007 vol. 29 1 179-184</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While referencing this website may look like this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Chatting, T (2016) ‘quick and dirty referencing’, <em>tom</em> [Online], Available: <a href="http://tomchatting.github.io/article/2016/02/23/quick-and-dirty-referencing.html">http://tomchatting.github.io/article/2016/02/23/quick-and-dirty-referencing.html</a> [23 Feb 2016]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Your reference list should be organised in alphabetical order (by author’s surname)
or in logical order (the order in which you referenced them in the body).</p>

<h2 id="let-your-references-run-free">let your references run free</h2>

<p>The tl;dr of all this is please reference or you will fail/have an academic
integrity review and that will be a bad thing. There is no ‘good’ number of
references to aim for, but there is no such thing as too many references.</p>

<hr />

<p>Layout and some examples taken from the University of Exeter’s Study Skills guide
to referencing found <a href="https://education.exeter.ac.uk/dll/studyskills/harvard_referencing.htm">here</a>.</p>

<p>A fantastic tool for creating reference guides/bibliographies is <a href="http://www.neilstoolbox.com/bibliography-creator/">Neil’s Toolbox</a>, to which I would
like to credit my entire degree.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Kanye West 30 Hours</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2016/02/14/kanye/"/>
   <updated>2016-02-14T10:33:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2016/02/14/kanye</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/246700455&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe>

<p>The Life of Pablo has finally dropped, it’s up for streaming/download on Tidal, and in one week it’ll hit all good streaming services. Old Kanye West seems to be back, I just hope he lets us in on the right memes.</p>

<p><a href="https://kanyewest.tidal.com"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/MG8vpPd.png" alt="Kanye West laughs at your conventions of fair currency conversion" /></a></p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The December update</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2015/12/16/december-update/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2015/12/16/december-update</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="650" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/B5YNiCfWC3A" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>Hold up: this one could get weird again.</p>

<h2 id="shit-ive-realised">Shit I’ve realised:</h2>

<ul>
  <li>I’ve used a Mac for nearly a year, after being the opposite of an Apple shill for years</li>
  <li>I’ve used an iPhone for longer. <strong>What is wrong with me?</strong></li>
  <li>The real way to format lists is as follows:</li>
</ul>
<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-css" data-lang="css"><span class="nt">ul</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">ol</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">dl</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nl">margin-bottom</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">1rem</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="nl">padding-left</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">40px</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="nt">li</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nl">margin-bottom</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">0.25rem</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<ul>
  <li>I’m twenty four in less than four months</li>
  <li>I probably wouldn’t survive the Commonwealth as long as I have in Fallout 4</li>
  <li>The font/size for optimal reading on the web is up for debate, but <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">18px/1.5 sans-serif</code> seems like a fairly good bet</li>
  <li>Pagination should run from Newest-Oldest/Left-Right, because if it were page numbers it’d go 1-x; also western=left-right writing</li>
  <li>Making lists is an easy way to fill a blog post</li>
</ul>

<p>Merry Holiday, I’ll write again next year* (*maybe)</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Jf9sGwr.png" alt="" /></p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Supporting in Season 2015</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2015/05/03/season-2015-supporting/"/>
   <updated>2015-05-03T22:14:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2015/05/03/season-2015-supporting</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/59824094&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe>

<p>Ah Season 2015, smiting champions, Cinderhulk, super-mega-special-super-special-awesome Baron buff, Dragon stacks and <em>crazy ass</em> support builds. Let’s jump in head first!</p>

<h3 id="just-buy-this-and-win">Just buy this and win</h3>

<blockquote>
  <h3 id="righteous-glory-2500g">Righteous Glory 2500g</h3>
  <p>UNIQUE ACTIVE: Grants +60% Movement Speed to you and nearby allies when moving towards enemies for 3 seconds. When this speed boost ends, it emits a shockwave, slowing nearby enemy champions by 80% for one second. 60 second cooldown.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I will legitimately be shocked if Righteous Glory goes without a nerf or three before the seasons end; it gives champions with normally zero chase-engage (Annie, Morgana) a Shurelya’s Reverie (or Talisman or Ascension) combined with a Randuin’s Omen. Hell, once you’ve finished it, you might as well take a Talisman and a Randuin’s anyway and just stack that sucker up!</p>

<h3 id="theres-building-boots-and-buying-a-ward-on-first-back-and-theres-an-incorrect-back">There’s building boots and buying a ward on first back and there’s an incorrect back</h3>

<p>Roaming and edging advantages means more than ever this season, games are incredibly hard to close out when even with tower buffs, the easiest way to do this is the roam for ward placement/cheeky ganks on mid. Or you know… do it at level one.</p>

<iframe width="650" height="356" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jarSwNKBhfA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h3 id="what-the-fuck-is-that-build">“What the fuck is that build…”</h3>

<p>Zero AP Annie/Morgana sounds like trash, but support this season isn’t about carrying with damage, it’s about carrying with <a href="http://matchhistory.euw.leagueoflegends.com/en/#match-details/EUW1/2092496922/36795625?tab=stats">utility</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/CNX5hZN.png" alt="" /></p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Tom does reading: Hard-Boiled Wonderland and the End of the World</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2014/11/07/hard-boiled-wonderland-and-the-end-of-the-world/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-07T23:11:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2014/11/07/hard-boiled-wonderland-and-the-end-of-the-world</id>
    <content type="html"><h3 id="how-i-fell-in-love-with-murakami">How I fell in love with Murakami</h3>

<p>In my quest to invest myself more heavily in Japanese culture (beyond Japanese game shows and manga) I decided to plunge into the world of Japanese literature. After much thought and blurb-reading, I happened upon <em>Hard-Boiled Wonderland and the End of the World</em> by Haruki Murakami. The author, speculated to have been shortlisted for the Nobel Prize for Literature multiple times, is said to be “poetic” in his writing style; easy to read, yet thought-provoking and impactful. I was told to expect a mix of “western-style fantasy” and “science-fiction mystery”, and boy, does Murakami deliver.</p>

<p>The novel follows two narratives which standalone and later intertwine: <em>Hard-Boiled Wonderland</em> tells the story of a successful corporate/government agent, dutifully fulfilling his set tasks whilst enjoying an almost pragmatic lifestyle, in a tone not dissimilar to the narrators in <em>The Humans</em> or <em>The Curious Tale</em>. <em>The End of the World</em> tells the tale of a lost soul, who departs with his shadow to gain entry to a town at the end of the world. He is given the task of “dream reading” until such a time his shadow dies, and he can become immortal and “at one” with the town which protects him from the outside world that all within strive to forget.</p>

<p>The pure beauty of Murakami’s writing is that even within the translation, subtleties creep in. It took me half a dozen chapters (and a re-read of two) to realise the author never actually divulges the name of a single character, yet his writing style and descriptive narrative leave me questioning whether a name is ever needed. The author also switches between the personal past tense and present tense in alternate chapters in such a subtle way, leaving a strong satisfaction as you try to puzzle the ending together.</p>

<p>A fascinating mystery science-fiction adventure with an ending that leaves you to think. <em>Hard-Boiled Wonderland and the End of the World</em> is a fantastic introduction to an obviously strong writer and, as my new copy of <em>A Wild Sheep Chase</em> suggests, is a great gateway novel to more of the same.</p>

<p>♦ 4.5/5</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Hard-Boiled Wonderland and the End of the World is available on <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Hard-Boiled-Wonderland-End-World-International/dp/0679743464">Amazon</a> and all good book stores</li>
  <li>For Japanese game shows I highly recommend <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/japanesegameshows">/r/japanesegameshows</a></li>
  <li>My current manga of choice is <em>Deadman Wonderland</em>, review of part one coming soon™</li>
</ul>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Lazy scaling for lazy people</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2014/08/09/lazy-scaling-for-lazy-people/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-09T00:26:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2014/08/09/lazy-scaling-for-lazy-people</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="640" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/qAkasSdD4M0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>While device optimisation appears to be the Flavour of The Year(TM) effort for web developers, many (such as I) may find this laborious.</p>

<h2 id="smack-it-with-snippets-until-it-works">Smack it with snippets until it works</h2>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-html" data-lang="html">    <span class="nt">&lt;meta</span> <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">"viewport"</span> <span class="na">content=</span><span class="s">"width=device-width, user-scalable=no"</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>The above demands mobile browsers (namely Safari and Chrome) back-off on their normal charade of imitating fullscreen browsers, and instead report their true width to the CSS, meaning users are served what is considered a “mobile” friendly site.</p>

<p>This is only one part of the puzzle, however, since you will still need to scale your content in CSS accordingly.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-css" data-lang="css"><span class="nc">.wrapper</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nl">max-width</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">38rem</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nl">margin</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">0</span> <span class="nb">auto</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nl">padding-left</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">2%</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nl">padding-right</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">2%</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Something like the above keeps your site running at most resolutions with minimum work. Of course, it’s still recommended you scale fonts and the like using media queries; but we’re far too lazy for that now, aren’t we?</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New design, or Tom inside</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2014/05/04/tom-inside/"/>
   <updated>2014-05-04T00:44:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2014/05/04/tom-inside</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="640" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/6YZlFdTIdzM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>Please excuse the live changes I’m making to the site. I’ve upgraded my PC, updated my CV, and got the itch to redesign this site. Hang tight.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>HP Chromebook 11</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2014/01/07/chromebook/"/>
   <updated>2014-01-07T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2014/01/07/chromebook</id>
    <content type="html"><p>I’ve had my eye on the <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/intl/en_uk/chrome/devices/hp-chromebook-11/">Google/HP Chromebook 11</a> ever since it was announced and launched late 2013. In December, however, the device was recalled due to reports of the charger <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/11/13/5099570/best-buy-removes-hp-chromebook-11-from-stores">overheating, melting, and in some cases burning users</a>. So of course, being the impatient guy I am, I bought a “used for one week” Chromebook with a faulty charger from eBay for the steal price of £190 (RRP is £229 and, as of writing, is still not available). Being away from University over the holidays means I’ve been away from my gaming PC, leading the Chromebook to be my main machine for the past week or so; so I thought it’d be good to offload some details/feelings about the device.</p>

<h2 id="this-is-the-best-screen-on-any-device-ive-used">This is the best screen on any device I’ve used.</h2>

<p>Hands down, the 1366x768 IPS display is the best screen on any device I’ve ever used. Ever. I’m still not used to how high the pixel density is, nor am I used to the incredible brightness (I have to have the device at 80% brightness even when plugged in). Small text is clear, fonts are beautifully rendered, blacks are black and colours are bright and vibrant. You’d be looking at paying for a retina Macbook or iPad for screen quality <em>this</em> good on any other device.</p>

<h2 id="the-year-old-exynos-5-still-screams">The year old Exynos 5 still screams</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/7o8ujnf.png" alt="Meta" /></p>

<p>The Samsung Exynos 5 dual-core ARMv7 processor the Chromebook contains is the exact same chip that’s inside the Samsung Series 3 from 2012 (which is still on sale at a slightly lower price today), and it’s performance shows why Google chose it over putting something newer (and therefore, more expensive) inside the 11. As of writing, I have a Chrome port of Brackets, the code editor I use, called <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/tailor/mfakmogheanjhlgjhpijkhdjegllgenf/related?hl=en">Tailor</a> running, Spotify playing, and 4 other tabs open in Chrome. Many times I can have two Twitch streams playing at “source” resolution (generally 1080p) without the Chromebook skipping a beat. This is <strong>insane</strong>, my mother’s £600 Pavillion laptop running Windows 8.1 can’t do this, my £550 year old gaming rig can barely do this, I don’t know if it’s down to Windows vs Chrome OS or just the ability of the CPU, but this is insanity. Strangely, the Chromebook does struggle when playing audio with Google Play Music’s flash player when scrolling through heavy sites like <a href="http://theverge.com">The Verge</a>, but a couple of seconds of stuttering isn’t annoying enough to warrant a rant.</p>

<p>The speakers for the device are <em>under</em> the keyboard, and produce pretty solid stereo sound, on a par with a cheap set of external speakers, but far better than any previous laptop/phone I’ve used.</p>

<h2 id="the-inputs">The inputs</h2>

<p>Dual microphone/headphone jacks are something I’m not used to on laptops, they’re more akin to a tablet or a smartphone, but then again, this laptop is basically a Nexus 10 inside a laptop shell, this means I’m also not as surprised that the Chromebook 11 supports micro-usb charging. At times, USB charging is incredibly handy: every friends or family members house I go to has a micro-USB cable lying around so I’m never without juice, but anything less than a 3 amp charger produces a warning on the device that more power will be used than can be provided, so charging will only occur when it’s turned off. Other than that, the device sports two USB 2.0 ports. And that’s it. HDMI output is possible via the micro-USB port, but dual power/video splitters cost in the region of £20, so unless I become desperate to stream South Park onto a bigger monitor, I won’t be investing in that.</p>

<p>If the display weren’t so incredible, I would spend hours raving about this keyboard. Full size, chicklet style keys (a la Macbook) and lacking keys I never use (search replaces caps lock, Chrome specific keys replace F1-12), I can comfortably write for hours on the device. But therein can lie a problem.</p>

<h2 id="juice-may-be-an-issue">Juice may be an issue</h2>

<p>If you’re like me and can type consistently for several hours, you may hit a snag on a coach or train trip. Google specifies “up to 6 hours of active use”. I can manage 7 at a pinch, but this isn’t a device that could, say, go days without a charge like a Nexus 7. The charger being micro-USB also produces an issue since charging to full from 10-20% can take up to 4 hours with the device on, so I’ve found myself using my Nexus 4 charger overnight with the device off.</p>

<h2 id="there-is-no-longer-such-a-thing-as-offline">There is no longer such a thing as “offline”</h2>

<p>The biggest argument against Chromebooks it seems is a mystical condition known as “offline syndrome”. While the OS and its various apps now sport offline support/modes, I simply cannot think of a situation where I am offline for more than 30 minutes in a position I might want to use my laptop. With unlimited data on my phone and bluetooth/WiFi tethering, unless I’m headed through a tunnel or travelling to remote Cumbria, in 2014 I think there’s seldom a place you can be without data/WiFi (and if you are, a Starbucks/McDonalds with free WiFi is never far away).</p>

<h2 id="this-is-my-usage-yours-may-vary">This is my usage, yours may vary</h2>

<p>It is difficult to tell someone a Chromebook would work for them, because it depends on your use case. In my case, I needed a laptop that could use <a href="http://jstorrent.com/">torrents</a>, git (included in <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/tailor/mfakmogheanjhlgjhpijkhdjegllgenf/related?hl=en">Tailor</a>), some form of document editor (included with Google Docs), the web, and last at least 6 hours without juice (since I have a gaming PC for the rest) and the Chromebook 11 hits all these points. So, <strong>go Scroogle yourself Microsoft</strong>.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Objects in mirror are losing</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/photo/2013/11/28/objects-in-mirror-are-losing/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-28T22:54:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/photo/2013/11/28/objects-in-mirror-are-losing</id>
    <content type="html"><p>From <a href="http://coolmaterial.com/rides/objects-in-mirror-are-losing-decals/">Cool Material</a></p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>League of Legends: Supporting 101, a pre-season update</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2013/11/28/supporting-part-2/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-28T22:30:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2013/11/28/supporting-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><div class="callout callout-warning">
As alluded to previously, here's another post on the popular <abbr title="Multiplayer online battle arena">MOBA</abbr> <a href="//leagueoflegends.com">League of Legends</a> with the aim of updating/rewriting some things from my <a href="http://dg9t.eu/article/2013/07/31/supporting-101.html">previous post</a> on how to support. As before, feel free to skip over this one. -- Tom
</div>

<iframe width="668" height="376" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/Ebz0lVVbRho" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>Season 4 pre-season is here, and boy is it a doozy. If you haven’t already, I highly recommend hitting up the <a href="http://euw.leagueoflegends.com/en/news/game-updates/patch/patch-314-notes">3.14 patch notes</a> or dropping into a few games in normal queue before playing ranked (<em>hypocrite alert, I just dove straight in</em>).</p>

<h2 id="new-season-new-pre-game">New season, new pre-game</h2>

<p>I’ve branched out a tad, not only being forced to change my masteries (I still feel 0/13/17 is the best, for now) but also my runes.</p>

<p>I run three rune pages depending on the situation/champion I’m playing:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Health, MR/level+Armour, and Gold/10</strong> - For champions like Blitz and Sona that got heavily nerfed last season as far as aggression is concerned (base HP nerfs), or in match-ups against high early level burst like Blitz or Graves</li>
  <li><strong>AP, Armour+Flat MR, and Magic Pen</strong> - For champions like Lulu and Sona who can glass cannon lane around levels 1-6 really hard. Even post nerf Sona can 100-50 any carry with a good <em>Q-Power Chord-Q</em> combo</li>
  <li><strong>Old school Gold, Flat AD, and MR/level+Armour</strong> - Running Gold Quints, and taking flat AD to get some more heavy poke on</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="who-works-now-who-doesnt">Who works now, who doesn’t</h2>

<p>I’ve always been a believer in the idea that there is no such thing as a counter if you are good enough with someone. Regardless; Blitz still counters Sona, Lulu counters Leona, and Thresh just <em>shits</em> on everyone.</p>

<p>As far as the mages go (Annie, Lux, Nidalee); the same high risk/high reward system applies. If you can secure the kills and more importantly the <strong>gold</strong>, you can win a game just from bot lane. If you do not, you fall off: simple as.</p>

<h2 id="so-whos-the-strongest">So who’s the strongest?</h2>

<p>At the minute I believe it comes down to personal preference. High win rates can be found on Leona, Annie, Thresh, and Janna. Play someone who matches your style, or duo with someone you can effectively communicate with, because communication is more OP than a difficult lane match-up.</p>

<h2 id="starting-items-and-builds">Starting items and builds</h2>

<p>Thanks to the new trinkets and gold items (<em>and gold income</em>) support is incredibly diverse and actually exciting at the moment. As of writing, <em>Spoils of War</em> has been nerfed–after it was discovered how ridiculous a ranged support <em>and</em> a marksman were when both started with it–to apply to melee auto-attacks only, but the item is still incredibly strong (think of a healing Leona/Blitzcrank).</p>

<p>My builds tend to focus on either offence or defence now, building a gold item and a sightstone first, then focussing on something like a Rabadon’s Deathcap or a DFG if it’s going well (The AP Mage’s “support” abilities like slows and stuns now scale from AP), or a Randuin’s Omen, Frozen Heart, Banshee’s Veil if more defensive stats are needed.</p>

<h2 id="wards-are-still-op">Wards are still OP</h2>

<p>With the new limit on 3 wards and a pink per champion, you need to be making sure you not only keep on top of your own warding, but try to <em>nicely</em> suggest your team-mates do the same.</p>

<h2 id="good-luck-have-fun">Good luck, have fun.</h2>

<p>So there’s a fix-up for the previous post. It’s a bit mashed up and a lot of things need clarification, but Season 4 is a long way away, and there’s much more to learn and many more games to play.</p>

<h2 id="one-more-thing-i-made-gold-ii-again">One more thing, I made Gold II (again)!</h2>

<p>Duo queueing with a friend trying to get to Gold, branching out to top lane and AD carry for about 30% of my games (and sometimes winning even those games!), and being more confident in shot-calling has landed me back in Gold II. My aim is to reach Plat by Season 4 placement. Wish me luck!</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>League of Legends: Season 4 support masteries</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/photo/2013/11/24/league/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-24T19:31:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/photo/2013/11/24/league</id>
    <content type="html"><p>From the few days I’ve had playing League in the new pre-season I think this is probably one of the better mastery pages to run. I’ll post an updated rundown on how to support in the new season soon™.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>:not()</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/link/2013/11/24/css-now/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-24T17:20:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/link/2013/11/24/css-now</id>
    <content type="html"><p>A quick <em>how-to</em> on using the :not() selector in CSS.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Yorkshire hills by my friend Alex</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/photo/2013/11/24/huddersfield-photo/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-24T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/photo/2013/11/24/huddersfield-photo</id>
    <content type="html"><p>This is a photo from atop a hill my housemate Alex rode during one of his many cycle-hype induced runs.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Life</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2013/11/02/life/"/>
   <updated>2013-11-02T00:57:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2013/11/02/life</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="640" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/Oww-7cxOBUk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>It’s been three months since my last blog post, so I thought I’d post some updates on my life <sup>and excuses for not posting</sup>.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Fbqgtaz.png" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="what-is-life">What is life</h2>

<ul>
  <li>As of October 29th, I am an official (temporary) employee at a leading supermarket chain (hence the corporate banner colour)</li>
  <li>I hit Gold II at my peak in League of Legends (I’m currently Gold III due to sucking pretty hard, but I’m quite pleased with my progress. Next up: Platinum!)</li>
  <li>Third year at University has forced me to hit the ground running, and that’s been pretty tough so far. But so far, so good.</li>
  <li>I <em>still</em> haven’t got the new Facebook experience</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="coming-up">Coming up</h2>

<p>In the pipe for the blog: some more bigoted, elitist, views on my climb through the ranks in League (and why how self deprecating I am IRL has helped), some Chemistry/Pharmacy stuff (good excuse for revision), and some more random YouTube embeds from music I think you should listen to–because my taste in music is the <em>correct</em> taste in music.</p>

<p>Ttyl; bbiab,</p>

<p>Tom &lt;3</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Google Play Music All Access: terrible title, terrific service</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2013/08/09/google-play-music-all-access/"/>
   <updated>2013-08-09T14:30:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2013/08/09/google-play-music-all-access</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="640" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/2o-bAHQs1cc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/sVWe3ny.png" height="300px" class="float-left" /></p>

<p><a href="https://play.google.com/about/music/">Google Play Music All Access</a> may well hold the title for being the worst named product in Google history, but for £7.99 a month with a 30 day free trial it may also well be the best-value product in Google history.</p>

<p>Plugging straight into the app on your Android device, the service turns your device into an all-containing jukebox. Songs and albums can be played on a one off basis or added to your library (or device offline) at the press of a button. The service is also available for use via Google’s web “app” on desktops and Chrome devices.</p>

<p>The Radio feature works much like Spotify Radio or Pandora, and is so far proving to be a great music discovery method, with the added benefit of being able to download a local copy of any song you like in case you go through a tunnel or land in North Korea.</p>

<p>Speaking of North Korea, there’s some great documentaries on visiting the hermit nation by <a href="http://www.vice.com/the-vice-guide-to-travel/vice-guide-to-north-korea-1-of-3">Vice on YouTube</a>.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Abort the mission, I've fallen in love with Jekyll</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2013/08/06/the-plan-has-failed/"/>
   <updated>2013-08-06T19:50:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2013/08/06/the-plan-has-failed</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="640" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/PF-_H54mydE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>When I initially did the setup routine and migrated my previous blog to Jekyll, I saw it as a temporary thing while I redeveloped my bespoke blog engine “SquareCMS”. What I didn’t anticipate was falling in love with the workflow of, developing for, and writing with <a href="//jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>.</p>

<h2 id="a-geeks-platform">A geeks platform</h2>

<p>Also known as a “hackers” platform, Jekyll really is designed to be tinkered and messed with. Unlike with SquareCMS, I have an easily tinkered with testing environment (my home PC running Ruby) that is (most unlike PHP/MySQL development) easily synced with the running–“<em>live</em>”–environment.</p>

<h2 id="unless-you-need-extra-features-generated-flat-files-are-fine">Unless you need extra features, generated flat files are fine</h2>

<p>“Compiled” in around a second or so on my machine, and uploaded in less than a minute, my entire site is now a group of flat, procedurally generated files. Think about it: do you <em>really</em> need a server-side computer generating the same page for every visitor <strong>every</strong> time they visit? Not especially. I don’t need plugins, multiple authors, server side management, search; I just need a quick-to-use, quick-to-post-to, easy-to-tinker site, and Jekyll provides it.</p>

<p>Abort the mission, I’ve fallen in love with Jekyll.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Oscar Wilde</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/quote/2013/08/04/oscar-wilde/"/>
   <updated>2013-08-04T11:22:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/quote/2013/08/04/oscar-wilde</id>
    <content type="html"><blockquote>
  <p>Most people are other people. Their thoughts are someone else’s opinions, their lives a mimicry, their passions a quotation.</p>
</blockquote>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The banner image took too long to load so here's a fun video and a new banner colour</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/link/2013/08/04/alt-j-dissolve-me/"/>
   <updated>2013-08-04T10:20:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/link/2013/08/04/alt-j-dissolve-me</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="640" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/0jfmwYNq_cg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>Changing the source of the stylesheet gives me a great excuse to push a post at the same time.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>League of Legends: Supporting 101</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2013/07/31/supporting-101/"/>
   <updated>2013-07-31T11:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2013/07/31/supporting-101</id>
    <content type="html"><div class="callout callout-warning">
A lot of information in this post is now out of date due to a massive rework of the support role. It's a good idea to read my <a href="//dg9t.eu/article/2013/11/28/supporting-part-2.html">updated notes</a> once you've blasted through this.
</div>

<iframe width="640" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/oIIxlgcuQRU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>Way back last year when lower jungle camps still spawned at 1:40, and the huge success of the season 2 world finals were just a pipe dream at the back of Tryndamere’s mind, I bit the bullet and signed up for LoL.</p>

<p>I find it fitting that I joined League the week Lulu was released, because (by my will or otherwise) I’ve found myself time and time again <abbr title="(To play a lot/be the strongest at)">maining</abbr> supports. Keep in mind that I’m currently climbing the Elo ladder for the first time–as a person who played with 3-5 friends at a time ranked seemed irrelevant to me–but I’d like to share my thoughts/feelings/insights into the support role.</p>

<h2 id="support-styles">Support styles</h2>

<p>I guess I can categorise a few different support styles in blanket terms, in theory all supports can match all styles:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Safe</strong> – Soraka, Sona, Taric, Lulu, Janna</li>
  <li><strong>Gun-ho</strong> – Blitzcrank, Thresh, Taric, Leona</li>
  <li><strong>Counter-aggressive</strong> – Blitzcrank, Leona, Taric, Thresh, Lulu, Sona (post level 6)</li>
</ul>

<p>Safe supports let your ADC/Marksman farm all day long, with you just popping their mana/hp back to full and stopping any threats with a quick stun, damage reduction spell, or just by having wards and good awareness of when champions are charging an auto attack.</p>

<p>Gun-ho supports grab the enemy marksman (sometimes literally) and try-hard to leave them on a platter for their own marksman to mop-up an easy kill.</p>

<p>Counter-aggressive supports play safe until initiated on, they then turn the tide and become gun-ho themselves.</p>

<h2 id="how2supp0rt">How2supp0rt</h2>

<p>The “easiest” support champion I could recommend at the moment is Leona. If you’re <abbr title="Re-climbing the Elo ladder on a second account">smurfing</abbr> and need a champion for every role, buy Leona for support. She’s seldom banned and easily the strongest support in the game.</p>

<h3 id="runes">Runes</h3>

<p>I swear by Gold runes. They are very expensive though so you don’t need to necessarily buy them if you’re smurfing, but if you’re planning on playing more than one support, I highly recommend you buy Gold Quintessences.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/14fWefZ.png" alt="Example rune page" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Wait, why no Gold yellows?</strong><br />
While gold quintessences give you +3 GP10 (<em>Philo gives you +5/10 as a comparison</em>), nine gold yellows only add +2 GP10, which may sound like a lot, but leaves you missing out on 12 armour which armour yellows could be providing. That’s the difference between an auto attack killing you, and leaving you with enough health to return to base.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="masteries">Masteries</h3>

<p>I like to go <a href="http://i.imgur.com/YJ9zmye.jpg">1/12/17 for melee supports</a> and <a href="http://i.imgur.com/jLFzwF7.jpg">5/0/25 for ranged</a>, with a completed Utility tree and more cooldown reduction for ranged supports and a slightly sacrificed Utility tree and more defence points for melee (the explanation shouldn’t be necessary).</p>

<h3 id="playing-leona">Playing Leona</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/AE9oErN.gif" alt="Playing Leona" /></p>

<p>Level Shield of Daybreak (Q), Zenith Blade (E) , Eclipse (W). Max W first followed by Q. Your “combo” is to activate your Q and W, then E onto the enemy marksman and let things happen. Your ultimate is great at locking down enemies, or slowing/stopping them when they try to run. Remember Solar Flare stuns enemies trapped in the centre, and slows enemies around it.</p>

<h3 id="beating-leona">Beating Leona</h3>

<p>In ranked, counter Leona with champions like Soraka, Lulu, Alistar, and Janna. These heroes all have interrupts, heals and/or shields to disrupt and fix the damage from a Leona.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/UbZnDdM.gif" alt="Beating Leona" /></p>

<p>A quick E, W, Q combo can protect your carry from Leona, and deal tonnes of damage in return.</p>

<h2 id="the-support-mindset">The support mindset</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Watching people like Krepo and XPecial and Madlife, you’d think all support heroes were point-and-click, you’d never guess from a glance that Thresh, Lulu, Blitzcrank and more all have skillshots.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The first biggest misconception I’ve ever seen in League is that “support is easy”, and I want to shut that one down straight away. No matter what way you look at it, early game, <abbr title="Formerly ADCs or AD Carries">marksmen</abbr> <strong>suck</strong>. I’d even go far as saying that early game, the support is <em>stronger</em> than their lane partner. This is highlighted with the fact that when you look at your death recap as a marksman after first blood, you’ll see <em>Leona</em> probably did 50%+ of the total damage, with that pesky Ezreal mopping up with a strategic Q or <abbr title="Auto Attack">AA</abbr>. Now, watching people like Krepo and XPecial and Madlife, you’d think all support heroes were point-and-click, you’d never guess from a glance that Thresh, Lulu, Blitzcrank and more all have skillshots. But, no. Support is not easy. As a support you not only have to be a move ahead of your marksman, you have to have wards timed and accounted for, cooldowns stacked in your head, minimap awareness, strong <abbr title="The idea that you make the enemy know you're there by poking and harassing">lane-presence</abbr>, and the mind-set that when it comes to it, you will die for your marksman.</p>

<h3 id="going-1-6-isnt-that-bad">Going 1-6 isn’t that bad</h3>

<p>Yesterday, I had a game which was a prime example of this. As Thresh, I had a Tristana in my lane who managed to finish laning phase 0-0 with higher farm than the enemy Vayne who was 4-0. The junglers had left bot alone, we had struggled from the start and I conceded first blood. I finished laning phase 0-4. GG, right? Perhaps not. League is a game about pressure, CS, objectives, and <strong>morale</strong>. Laning phase ended, Tristana picked up a shutdown bonus on Vayne and the team picked on her after that, and we shut her down hard. The idea that you if you can sometimes just throw yourself in the way of the marksmans inevitable death isn’t just a noble afterthought, it’s a calculated decision. I’m not saying suicide and go 0-10, far from it, I’m saying if you dying–and “feeding” as our Nidalee so eloquently put it–keeps your carry alive and able to outfarm under the tower, it’s less a “suicide” and more a “calculation”.</p>

<p>Your greatest asset as a support is your kit. Learn your Q through R, buy items like Aegis (upgrade it to a Locket), Randuin’s, Zeke’s Herald, Twin Shadows, Mikael’s Crucible etc. Have trouble remembering? Make a custom item set, you want something that looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/g1jfTZ7.png" alt="How to support" /></p>

<p>Keep your carry alive, keep yourself alive (unless you need a “calculated death”), <strong>secure the kills for the team, then your carry</strong>. By that, I mean, only leave a kill if you are certain your carry can lasthit it. If you’re on Skype or TeamSpeak, great, they’re going to be telling you straight away if you need to lasthit; on solo queue, it’s more of a gained skill. As a rule in thumb: when in doubt, just do as much damage as you can, even if it means <em>taking the kill</em>. At the end of the day, assist gold is better than no gold for your carry/jungler/roaming mid/tp’ing top laner.</p>

<h3 id="wards-are-not-an-optional-endeavour">Wards are not an optional endeavour</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/hX27BeQ.jpg" alt="Minimum wards" /></p>

<p>The sightstone is an incredible item. If you’re not building it first you should be building it either directly after your gold item or at the same time as level 1 boots. When you b, always buy a pink and a couple of pots if you can. Mapped above are common locations for wards and smart locations for wards if you’re on bot lane, top lane can be translated similarly. <strong>Make bottom lane an impenetrable fortress for all but your team</strong>. (<em>NB: if the enemy purple team has a Zac, or Thresh, ward purple side tri bush to stop lantern/jump ganks.</em>)</p>

<h3 id="shield-supports-take-more-skill">Shield supports take more skill</h3>

<p>Yeah, you could be Soraka and just heal your carry back up to full after taking poke, or just sit there dancing as Sona giving your marksman an armour buff, but real men use shields. There is skill involved in noticing when an enemy is moving to auto attack your ally, there is skill involved in landing the shield down. The true secret, is to make your carry think “I didn’t take any damage from that <abbr title="Caitlyn's passive">headshot</abbr>”. This doesn’t necessarily mean you need to level your shield though, level one shields suffice on Lulu (Q or W can sometimes be better levelled), Thresh (E &gt; Q &gt; W), or even an aggressive Janna. Just make an early investment in an emblem of valour (just make sure to let your jungler know, else you’ll be buying <abbr title="Banner of command">promote</abbr>).</p>

<h3 id="theres-a-reason-you-get-35g-every-time-you-auto-attack">There’s a reason you get 3/5G every time you auto attack</h3>

<p>Harass. Poke. Prod. Annoy the hell out of the enemies. Do not just afk in the bush and wait for things to happen (unless that’s how your carry wants the lane to be played, in which case, disregard their instructions, see above.).</p>

<h2 id="remember-its-a-game">Remember it’s a game</h2>

<p>If it’s going badly, don’t sweat. If you’re getting flamed, mute them and report them. <strong>Good luck, have fun</strong>.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The world is (going) flat</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2013/07/29/the-world-is-going-flat/"/>
   <updated>2013-07-29T19:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2013/07/29/the-world-is-going-flat</id>
    <content type="html"><iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/mDdWm7mmhaA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="1"> </iframe>

<p>Call me a sheep but the world appears to be getting flatter, and I for one welcome the change.</p>

<h2 id="something-the-big-three-all-agree-on">Something the big three all agree on</h2>

<p>Apple, Google, and Microsoft have all taken steps towards flat interfaces with the advent of iOS 7, Android 4.0, and Windows 8 respectively, and they’re not the only ones. Twitter/Github’s <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/">Bootstrap</a>, and as such a <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/07/28/bootstrap-3-goes-mobile-first-now-reportedly-powers-1-of-the-web/">claimed 1% of the web, has followed suit</a>.</p>

<p>Pardon me for bandwagon-ing, but I see the pros for this trend and have tweaked by site <strong>again</strong> to follow, like the wool covered animal I am.</p>

<h2 id="a-few-other-changes">A few other changes</h2>

<p>I’ve finally fixed the paddings and spacing of the site, so it no longer hurts your eyes to separate the page, and I’ve now made my desktop and mobile background the header banner, the source is <a href="http://wallbase.cc/wallpaper/2901427">here</a> as well as in the footer. Oh, and I’ve removed the webfonts, just because I watched <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Il4swGfTOSM">this video</a> and took it a little to heart.</p>

<p>&lt;3 you all bbiab, Tom.</p>

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mobile Tech Rant</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2013/07/14/mobile-tech/"/>
   <updated>2013-07-14T15:20:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2013/07/14/mobile-tech</id>
    <content type="html"><h2 id="when-your-phone-is-more-powerful-than-your-laptop">When your phone is more powerful than your laptop</h2>

<p>I have two notebooks in my possession for “couch computing” and writing assignments when AFBC (away from behemoth computer). Their specs are rather modest, even for their generations. The larger of the two is a 2007 model 15” HP laptop sporting an AMD64 2.2GHz Dual Core processor, 2GB RAM and integrated Nvidia graphics with a max resolution of 1280x768, the smaller being a 7” Asus Eee PC sporting a 0.9GHz Intel 32-bit single core Celeron processor and a whopping 1GB RAM, with Intel “accelerated” graphics pumping out an impressively crisp 1024x600px resolution. Both these devices are over 5 years old, but let’s look at phones from 5 years ago: the HTC G1 had a 320x480 pixel display, a 0.528GHz processor (single core) and 192MB RAM, about comparable with computers at the turn of the <em>millennium</em> (although “gaming rigs” may have sported Intel Tualatin’s clocking 1.2GHz). Flash forward and  my Nexus 4 today has a <strong>quad core</strong> 1.51 GHz Snapdragon, 2GB RAM and a Qualcomm Adreno pumping  out 768x1184 pixels.</p>

<h2 id="the-pointtldr">The point/Tl;dr</h2>

<p>When mid-high range phones have caught up to low-mid range computers from just 5-6 years ago, when 5-6 years ago, they were nearly 10 years behind, you know the future of mobile tech is going to be awesome. (<em>Also, Moore’s law</em>)</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Digg Reader. Yes.</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2013/06/27/digg-reader/"/>
   <updated>2013-06-27T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2013/06/27/digg-reader</id>
    <content type="html"><p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DWhBj64.png" alt="Digg Reader" title="Digg Reader" /></p>

<p>I can’t believe I’m saying this, but I’ve signed back into an RSS service, and I am <em>loving</em> it.</p>

<p>Digg Reader, though apparently “lacking” in what Digg call a full feature-set, in it’s current standing the web-app more or less replicates <strong>everything</strong> I love about Google Reader.</p>

<p>Digg. Well fed.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Surviving Without Google Reader</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2013/06/25/surviving-without-reader/"/>
   <updated>2013-06-25T12:50:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2013/06/25/surviving-without-reader</id>
    <content type="html"><h2 id="rss-is-dead-long-live-rss">RSS is dead, long live RSS</h2>

<p>According to Google, I am a <a href="//googlereader.blogspot.co.uk/2013/03/powering-down-google-reader.html">dying statistic</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“usage of Google Reader has declined”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My daily routine for the past four or five years has involved checking-in with Google Reader every morning and every evening to catch up on sites that I either don’t visit (ex. <a href="//daringfireball.net"><em>Daring Fireball</em></a>), or don’t frequent enough to keep up with their onslaught of posts (ex. <a href="//theverge.com"><em>The Verge</em></a>). To me, RSS is one of the, if not <strong>the</strong>, best Internet technologies invented. It gives me the freedom to procure my own “top list” of sites and read them like an Internet-newspaper digest whenever I please. So imagine my dismay when I see:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/PsyHz5s.png" alt="Ugh..." /></p>

<p>If you haven’t heard, Google Reader will be “Sunsetted” on July 1st. To Google’s credit I was able to take away a copy of my OPML subscriptions list, but as I discovered, there’s few places to go.</p>

<h2 id="google-simultaneously-saved-and-killed-the-rss-reader-market">Google simultaneously saved and killed the RSS reader market</h2>

<p>Initially, I looked at services like Google’s <a href="//www.google.com/producer/currents">Currents</a>, and <a href="//flipboard.com/">Flipboard</a>; and hated them. My issue with these services is I may as well just be using the content providers websites, as Google Reader has solidly bred me into the camp where I just want a list of headlines from every source ordered chronologically which I can J and K through. I also tried <a href="//feedly.com">Feedly</a> and signed up for Digg’s <a href="//digg.com/reader">Reader</a>, but Feedly left me feeling overwhelmed with features I didn’t understand and weren’t documented, and Digg still haven’t rolled out their Reader due to what looks like <a href="//www.theverge.com/2013/6/21/4451644/diggs-very-beta-rss-reader-is-it-enough-to-woo-google-reader-users">issues</a> with the service.</p>

<p>There are services like Sean Inman’s <a href="//feedafever.com">Fever</a> and <a href="//tt-rss.org/redmine/projects/tt-rss/wiki">Tiny Tiny RSS</a>, but both are self-hosted and my current webspace provider doesn’t allow me to use all the features they require, though running one of them on a RaspberryPi may prove an interesting summer project.</p>

<h2 id="giving-up">Giving up</h2>

<p>Sadly, I did concede in the end and couldn’t persevere to find a good solution. I uninstalled the Google Reader app from my phone and removed it from the default tabs on Chrome. My information glut has begun.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/4nb5s4t.png" alt="Filling the gap" /></p>

<p>My only viable alternative for now has been to install <a href="//news.ycombinator.com">Hacker News</a> and <a href="//reddit.com">Reddit</a> apps, which I try to keep on top of at least 2-3 times a day, but sadly, much like it used to pre-Reader, news and information can just pass me by. (Luckily the big stuff like all the current Snowden malarky stays on the frontpages for long enough for me to pick up on.)</p>

<h2 id="asideor-wheres-my-feedxml-file">Aside–or “Where’s my feed.xml file?”</h2>

<p>On the topic of RSS but slightly aside from the main point; yes I am lacking an RSS feed for this site. Rest assured I’m hacking away at a solution and should be committing it to the Git repo Soon™.</p>

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hello World!</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/note/2013/06/19/hello-world/"/>
   <updated>2013-06-19T21:02:51+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/note/2013/06/19/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><p>Well here we go again.</p>

<p>Just in the meantime while I rework Square, I’m gonna be running Jekyll on Github for my ramblings and posts, and this time I <em>promise</em> to update. Again.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2013/06/09/welcome-to-jekyll/"/>
   <updated>2013-06-09T20:38:51+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2013/06/09/welcome-to-jekyll</id>
    <content type="html"><p>So here I am running <a href="http://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a>, a Ruby powered flat-blog generating static-site generator.</p>

<p>Jekyll wouldn’t be in my normal choices for a blog system as it runs on Ruby, but <a href="http://pages.github.com">GitHub Pages</a> allows you to host and run a Jekyll blog from one of you repositories with very little effort. Sweet!</p>

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Finding the perfect writing tool</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2013/01/17/finding-the-perfect-writing-tool/"/>
   <updated>2013-01-17T19:38:51+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2013/01/17/finding-the-perfect-writing-tool</id>
    <content type="html"><p>I’ve always enjoyed writing, but I’ve always found myself obsessing over the tool I use more than actually writing. This could mean spending more time trying to find the perfect pen and Moleskine, or more recently, constantly changing the CMS or blogging tool, or even the word processor I use.</p>
<h2 id="distraction-free-writing">Distraction Free Writing</h2>
<p>Markdown has long been a tool I’ve used to write things down in shorthand, and at one stage I used it as the default markup language for my blog posts; but of late I’ve realised it’s a fantastic way to push <em>distraction free writing</em> upon myself, which focuses on the content you are writing, rather than the implement you use. 
There are a multitude of available “Zen writers” available, several of which include their own soundtracks, which change depending on how fast you are typing (to really get you in the zone). The editor I’m using at the moment is called “Writer” and is available on the Google Play Store for Android phones and tablets. While you might think typing essays and blog posts on a phone keyboard could be a chore, I’ve found with Jelly Beans new swipe gesture keyboard my typing is actually faster than I can physically write, the biggest barrier to the speed is how much you trust the software; as I find the more often I check for errors, the slower I go.</p>

<blockquote>
  <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>   Ignore the surroundings, focus on the task in front of you
</code></pre></div>  </div>
</blockquote>

<p>I suppose if anything, my adventure in finding a better writing tool has led me to realise a few things: the simplest option is often the best, I’ll never be happy with my blogs design, and ignore the surroundings, focus on the task in front of you.</p>
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>In the case of evals in PHP</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/article/2012/03/07/in-the-case-of-php-evals/"/>
   <updated>2012-03-07T23:52:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/article/2012/03/07/in-the-case-of-php-evals</id>
    <content type="html"><blockquote>
  <p>The eval() language construct is very dangerous because it allows execution of arbitrary PHP code. Its use thus is discouraged. If you have carefully verified that there is no other option than to use this construct, pay special attention not to pass any user provided data into it without properly validating it beforehand.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Today I got a bit of a coding itch, it ended up in me having an epiphany in the shower of all places as to why in <em>hells</em> name I’d ever used <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">eval</code> in making SquareCMS, and how to fix it. After a lot of work this afternoon I’ve managed to rewrite <a href="https://github.com/tomchatting/SquareCMS/blob/master/square/controllers/theme.php">/controllers/theme.php</a> from scratch using functions to output text then displaying that to the user. Originally I did some rather recursive and <em>dangerous</em> stuff (see blockquote from PHP.net) within the theme file, using it to generate another PHP file within itself then using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">eval</code> to execute it within theme.php.</p>

<p>theme.php originally had a few functions or different roles. At it’s simplest, theme.php would always be called by a function using eval in a way such as:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>eval(echo 'themeFunction($file)';)  and would be passed a file in plain text, usually a theme file such as [this](https://github.com/tomchatting/SquareCMS/blob/master/square/themes/default/index.page) one. This file would then be stripped of all its' `&lt;square:tags /&gt;` by using regular expressions or simple find and replace functions, in these tags places would be the raw code required to do what the theme writer wanted to be present, for example `&lt;square:url /&gt;` returns the blogs' URL using the pre-set constant, but returns it as `'.URL.'` so the PHP can be executed (as if you look above the eval call is echoing the output) and leaves the next returned string able to do the same, leaving an even playing field. This file would then be saved to a variable, ready to be eval'd by the calling function.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Eval executes arbitrary PHP code, exactly as it would run as if you’d called it from the web browser or included it from another file; so it runs with the same privileges as such a file would if it were uploaded via FTP and executed. This produces an inherent problem particularly with something like a blog engine such as the one I made, not because you can generate execution issues (this is true, debugging with eval is much, much harder as I discovered) but because when you begin introducing user generated content like themes and plugins; security becomes a huge issue.</p>

<h2 id="trust-no-one">Trust No-One</h2>

<p>Herein lies the problem: if you allow a user to begin adding non-verified and non-tested components to your software, is it right to allow them to operate at the same execution level as the verified and tested components? Of course not, that’s suicide. If a malicious user were to set up a file or plugin that put the users server, or worse their <em>data</em> at risk, it wouldn’t be the fault of the user for installing such a component, nor would it be the malicious guy (well, it would, but that’s not the point) it’d be the jack-ass that allowed for this sort of stuff to happen in the first place.</p>

<p>So before anything like this was able to happen to anyone that may use/fork Square in the future, I decided to completely remove all evals from SquareCMS, and as of tomorrow on GitHub the code this server is running will be pushed into the Repo for review/proof.</p>

<h2 id="simple-take-out">Simple take-out</h2>

<p>The main conclusion to gain from this article/apology is not that you should never use evals, they can be quite useful for a variety of reasons, and in some cases they are the only solution to a problem; but you <strong>have</strong> to be 110% sure that all parameters are both correct (to save difficult debugging) and trusted, and in the case of third-party solutions being added to your project, you can guarantee neither, so a different option is often the better one.</p>

<p>For what it’s worth, it turns out SquareCMS runs around 0.01 seconds <em>slower</em> now it doesn’t run evals to parse themes, as it has to parse files two or three times separately due to the nature of how I construct pages from files, though I’m sure I can shave that back off down the road when I get my next itch.</p>

<p>1 <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/function.eval.php">http://php.net/manual/en/function.eval.php</a></p>
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
